The Aqua Infra project aims to develop a virtual environment equipped with fair
multidisciplinary data and services to support marine and freshwater scientists
and stakeholders in restoring healthy oceans, seas, coastal and inland waters.
The Aqua Infra virtual environment will enable the target stakeholders to store,
share, access, analyze and process research data and other research digital
objects from their own discipline across research infrastructures, disciplines
and national borders leveraging on EOS and the other existing operational data
spaces. Aqua Infra is addressing the specific need for enabling researchers
from the marine and freshwater communities to work and collaborate across those two
domains. a set of strategic use cases, including a Pan European use case as well
as more focused use cases in the Baltic Sea, the North Sea, and the
Mediterranean, will provide the setting for co-designing and testing services in the targeted research communities. This
training video focuses on the Gulf of Riga and the Daugava River catchment use case in the Baltic Sea region. by
presenting the story behind this compelling use case and its developed workflow. We will also introduce key
components of the Aqua Infra interaction platform and demonstrate how the data to
knowledge package concept is implemented within the Aqua Infra project. Coming up
next, the lead scientist involved in the research and development of this use case will present the story and outline
the main research
question. Hello, my name is Astra Labuce and I'm a researcher at Latvian
Institute of Aquatic Ecology. I'm currently involved in the Aqua Info project. Within this project,
researchers across Europe are working on many research questions and issues. And in our case, the research question began
with the story. A few years ago, scuba divers from our institute shared a personal
observation that the underwater world in the Gulf of Riga was becoming darker.
Naturally, there could be many explanations. One explanation they joked is that they are simply getting older
and their eyesight isn't what it used to be. But even so, the observation raised
a serious hypothesis. To begin answering the question, do the optical properties in
the Gulf of Riga change over the long term. We developed a reproducible and reusable workflow as part of Aqua
project. And because the largest river flowing into the Gulf of Riga is the river Daugava, we call this DGA
workflow. This workflow includes temporal and spatial aggregation, data interpolation, trend analysis, and some
visualizations. A key data set in this use case is the Secchi depth measurements. It's obtained by a simple method using a
Secchi disc. Basically, a black and white disc is lowered into the water and we
record the depth where it's no longer visible. And this shows us how transparent the water is and helps us
understand the amount of algae, tiny particles, and organic matter floating in it. The Gulf of Riga is a unique
marine environment. It's shallow, semi-enclosed, and exchanges water slowly with the open Baltic Sea. Because
of that, it's more strongly impacted by river runoffs and land-based activities. and seasonal changes like spring
nutrient inputs, summer algal blooms or winter ice have a major influence on its ecology. That's why time and seasonality
are central to our analysis. Coming up next, the Aqua Infra interaction
platform and the data to knowledge package related to the Gulf of Riga use case will be introduced.
This is the starting page of the Aqua Infra interaction platform. It serves as
the central gateway for scientific communities to find, access, and reuse
aquatic digital resources such as research data, tools, and workflows
associated with the Aqua Infra project. On the starting page, you will also find
basic training videos provided by the Aqua Infra development team offering
guidance on how to use the platform. Let's begin by exploring the search functionality to find resources related
to the Gulf of Riga workflow. In the search bar, enter your search term.
After clicking search, you will be redirected to a page where the search results are displayed.
To locate the data to knowledge package associated with the Gulf of Riga workflow, use data to knowledge as your
search term. On the search results page, you will find several options to filter
your results. First, there is the ontology search feature which categorizes the
results into four groups based on the relationship to the search term. You can
also filter results by data providers. The Aqua Infra interaction platform
includes resources from several data providers such as Inspire, Arctic Data
Center, Copernicus Marine, HELCOM, and EMODnet. You can narrow your search by
selecting one or more specific data providers. In addition, you can explore
the spatial coverage of the search results using the interactive map. You
can further refine your search area by selecting a European catchment
area or by drawing a custom bounding
box for our search related to the Gulf of Riga workflow. Select Zenodo as the
data provider and click search again to focus the results. All the necessary
materials to run and reproduce the Gulf of Riga workflow are available through the data to knowledge package for
reproducible spatiotemporal trend detection analysis. A data to knowledge package
links data and computational code to support a reproducible spatiotemporal
trend detection analysis. The selected package is specifically
designed to structure and integrate meta objects, providing a framework for
addressing the research question, do the optical properties in the Gulf of Riga in
the Baltic Sea change over the long term? Within the package, you will find
a step-by-step guide on how to run the workflow. You will also find links to a
MyBinder-based virtual lab and detailed information on the developed web API
services available in the virtual research environment section. The virtual lab provides a computational
environment based on the reproducible source code and data. It offers users a
ready to use setup with pre-installed packages allowing them to work with the
code directly within the MyBinder computational environment. In the web API section, you
can explore the toolbox associated with Spatio-temporal trend detection
analysis. It is accessible through platforms such as Zenodo and GitHub.
The toolbox includes a set of predefined functions designed for reproducible data
processing, statistical assessment, and visualization of results. It acts as the
computational backbone of the workflow, supporting the identification of long-term trends across spatial and
temporal scales. Finally, in the reproducible basis section, you will find detailed
information about the toolbox and the input data sets required to run the
workflow. The workflow is the first entry point for users to get an overview of the
analysis. To learn more about the data to knowledge package concept and how the workflow is structured, you can read the
open access method article written by the Aqua Infra development team. The
article is titled encouraging reusability of computational research
through data to knowledge packages a hydrological use case. Next we will
explore Aqua Galaxy the main component of the Aqua Infra virtual research
environment. We'll also take a closer look at the workflow section within the selected data to knowledge package.
Before starting a comprehensive review of the workflow components and steps, you first need to register in the Aqua
Galaxy. The Aqua Galaxy is a virtual research environment developed within
the Aqua Infra project. It is a subdomain within open-source web-based
Galaxy platform. It consists of a set of tools to analyze multidisciplinary fair
data and services to support marine and freshwater scientists and stakeholders
in restoring healthy oceans, seas, coastal and inland waters. The virtual
environment will enable target stakeholders to store, share, access,
analyze, and process research data and other digital research objects.
You can register here by filling in the required information. By staying signed in to
Aqua Galaxy, you can directly import the workflow and most of the Aqua Infra data
sets into the Aqua Infra research environment. We return to the data to
knowledge package page in the Aqua Infra interaction platform. Here by clicking
on the workflow you have several options to get detailed information about the workflow and to access and download
associated files. Selecting the Aqua Infra will take you to the workflow page on the interaction platform and the
detailed information about the workflow for Spatio-temporal trend detection analysis is provided on this page.
It also provides access to the workflow repository page in Zenodo. Here you have
access to the information about the workflow components and you can download the repository as a zip
file. It includes files such as text files including links to the results of
each step of the workflow to make it reproducible. The other file is the workflow file
compatible with the Aqua Galaxy and it can be used to import the workflow into
the virtual research environment. The other two options
associated with the workflow in the data to knowledge package page will take you to the reviewed repository page in
Zenodo and the workflow preview page in Aqua Galaxy. Next, we will explore the
workflow input data sets and learn how to import them into the Aqua Infra virtual research
environment. To begin running the workflow, we'll follow the steps outlined in the data to knowledge package.
Step one is to make sure you're signed into Aqua
Galaxy. Next, we need to import the required input data into the virtual research environment.
To import the point input data related to water transparency and Secchi measurements, start by clicking on
Latvian Secchi depth and water color. This gives you access to three
options. One is a direct download link for the point data. Another takes you to the Zenodo
page for the data to knowledge input data sets.
This includes both the Latvian Secchi depth and water color data set as well as the
HELCOM subbasins data set which can be downloaded here. Through the third one you can
visit the data set page on the aqua infra interaction platform where you'll
find basic details such as spatial coverage and metadata information. Since this data set is
already part of Aqua Infra, you can import it directly into Aqua Galaxy by
clicking the import to Galaxy. This opens the OGC API features
sub setting window where you can filter and select the data that will be imported. Here you can define a bounding
box to limit spatial coverage. Select the number of data points to
import or filter attributes using query
parameters. To answer the research question, we need all available data points
5,871 in total. So set the point number to
5,871. Click regenerate to receive the updated link. Then click import.
You will be redirected to the virtual research environment. The import may take some time to be deployed and be
implemented on the servers and be completed. Here in the history section,
a gray box means the step is cued. Orange means it's currently processing.
Green means the step is complete. And if there's an issue, the box will turn red.
Now let's return to the data to knowledge page to import the second data
set. Clicking on the second data set gives you similar
options. Click on the Aqua Infra to get access to the data set page on the interaction
platform where basic metadata is available.
Click visit to explore the original metadata. You'll find two useful links
here. One, a direct link to access the data
set. Two, a link to the HELCOM interactive map. Since this data set is
provided by HELCOM, it's not directly accessible through Aqua Infra data sets.
So you need to accept a data usage disclaimer first and follow some additional steps to import it into Aqua
Galaxy. The reason for this complexity is that some data providers do not yet
offer their data in a fully accessible or machine readable format.
To address this, the Aqua Infra development team must include additional
steps to ensure the data can be properly integrated and used within the virtual research environment. First, open the
direct download link from the metadata page in a new browser tab. Then accept the data usage
disclaimer. The download link will activate shortly afterward.
You don't need to download the file to your computer. Just copy the activated download
link. Return to the data set page on the interaction platform and paste the link into the
import field. Then click import. This will import the second data set into the
virtual research environment. Once the data is imported, it appears under a generic name like
Aqua Infra resource. It is a good idea to rename it for clarity. Click edit,
then rename the first data set to something meaningful, for example,
points. You can also add additional info or annotations
here. Once the box for the second data set turns green, go ahead and rename
this one to region. By clicking on the eye icon within each green box, you can access
the output. These are usually text files which include a link to the output of
each step. It's important to note that the data itself is not imported into the
Galaxy platform. Instead, users import only the access URL to the data. This
URL is then passed to the OGCAPI process which executes the
function and downloads the data as part of the process. For the point data set,
open the output link in a new browser tab to review it. You'll see that the Latvian Secchi depth and watercolor data
set is a point layer. Each point includes attributes such as latitude,
longitude, visit date, color ID, and transparency measured using the Saki
method. The second input data set provided by HELCOM includes water
assessment units at scale 4 delivered as a zip file. Inside it, you'll find a shape file of
the division of the Baltic Sea into 17 subbasins and further division into
coastal and offshore areas and division of the coastal areas by WFD water types
or water bodies.
As you can see, the import process for the second data set is completed and the
box turned green. As planned, let's rename it to
regions. The input data have been imported into the Aqua Infra virtual research environment. Let's return to
the interaction platform and import the workflow.
to import the workflow. In the workflow section in the interaction platform, click on Galaxy. As we've reviewed, this
will redirect you to the workflow preview page in Aqua Galaxy. Click on
import to complete the import process. On the next page, click on start using
this workflow and you'll be redirected to the main workflow section within Aqua
Galaxy. Alternatively, you can import the workflow manually. In the workflow section, each
workflow comes with multiple options. You can copy, download, share, or edit
them. By clicking edit, you can explore details about each workflow
component. Selecting a specific component reveals information about the step annotations and the underlying
processes. Let's run the workflow now. While it's running, we'll walk through
each component and step. Click run the workflow. You'll be taken to a page
where you can select input data. These data sets have already been
imported. Choose the point data set and the shape file polygons as region data.
Here another option is available for users by clicking on expand to full
workflow. You can also modify the input parameters for each step of the
workflow. After selecting the appropriate files, click run workflow.
You'll be taken to a progress page where you can monitor scheduled, running, and completed steps both through an
interactive workflow graph and the history section. The workflow begins
with the two input data sets, the point data and the polygon data. Next, the
pre-processing stage begins with spatial aggregation. In this step in situ, environmental data
points are assigned to spatial units based on the boundaries of the assessment unit
polygons. The data sets are merged and a new attribute is added to each point to
reflect its associated assessment unit. Clicking on each workflow step
shows details about inputs, outputs, and job metrics on the servers.
The next pre-processing step is temporal aggregation. It assigns a season to each
point based on the visit date and defined season's time interval. The output now includes a season attribute
for each data point. Then the data analysis starts. The first step is
calculate mean values by group one. Using the temporally aggregated data, it
calculates the average transparency for each group defined by season, year,
assessment unit ID, and location, and outputs the results as a CSV file. The
following step, calculate mean values by group 2, builds on this by further
averaging values for each assessment unit ID across seasons and years. The
result is a structured CSV file where each record corresponds to a single
transparency value for a specific unit, year, and season based on available
data. The next step is focusing on selecting time series with sufficient data and interpolating missing values.
First, any assessment unit with fewer than 10 data points is excluded.
Moreover, this step will analyze the available data points within each assessment unit through time series
length, which is the difference between the first and last year with data. If
the share of missing data is over 80% of the time series length, that unit is
also excluded. For the remaining units, missing values are interpolated across
the time series. This results in a structured time series data set
optimized for trend detection. The final data analysis step is Mann-Kendall trend
analysis. This non-parametric statistical test detects whether a data
set shows a significant upward or downward trend over time. The final
section of the workflow is visualization. It contains two steps.
The first uses the assessment unit polygons and the results from the spatial aggregation step to create an
interactive map. The second visualizes the man Kendall analysis results by
generating a bar chart that displays Kendall's tow values for the accepted
assessment unit. Next, we'll review the workflow results and wrap up this training video.
As you can see, all the boxes have turned green, indicating that every step of the workflow has been completed
successfully. Let's now review the results. By clicking on the eye icon in
each box, we can access the outputs, which are simple text files containing
links to the result of each step. Let's examine the result of the final
step in the data analysis, the man Kendall trend analysis. Clicking the provided link
will open a CSV file in a new browser tab and it will be downloaded
automatically. You can open this file in Excel or any other software that supports CSV files.
The Mann-Kendall trend test is a statistical method used to detect whether there is a
consistent increasing or decreasing trend in a time series of data such as
temperature, rainfall or water transparency. It is especially useful
for environmental and climate data because it does not require the data to follow a normal distribution and can
handle missing values or outliers. The test compares all possible pairs of
data points in the time series to determine if values tend to increase or decrease over time. The result is
expressed as a tow value which ranges from minus1 to + one. A tow value close to + one
indicates a strong increasing trend. A tow value close to minus1 indicates a
strong decreasing trend. A value near zero means there is no consistent trend.
The test also produces a p value which shows whether the trend is statistically
significant. If the p value is less than 0.05, the trend is considered
significant. In the results file, you will find the tow values and p values
for each accepted assessment unit with sufficient data. Now let's check the
visualization and identify which units show statistically significant changes in water
transparency. To do this, open the bar plot output by clicking on the eye icon
in the related box and follow the URL provided. As you can see, the bar chart
presents the trend analysis results using the same CSV file.
Units with statistically insignificant trends are shown with translucent
colors. Units with significant trends, meaning a p value below
0.05, are shown with solid fil bars. In this example, all three significant
results show a negative trend, which means water transparency has decreased.
Specifically, we observe negative trends in summer at
LA-00003 and LAT-004 and a similar negative trend in
autumn at LA-00005. Let's locate these three
assessment units on the interactive map generated by the workflow. Click the
output link provided in the relevant workflow step that is named map shape
file points. As you can see, all three assessment units are located along the
Latvian coastline. The LAT-05 unit includes the Daugava River
catchment which covers the coastal area near Ria, the capital of Latvia.
With this example, we have demonstrated how the data to knowledge package and workflow support the application of fair
principles in the Aqua Infra project. All data software and
processing steps are findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable.
For example, in the workflow run page, you can substitute your own data set that is compatible with this
workflow by clicking on expand to full workflow form. You can also adjust all
input parameters for each step such as the threshold for missing values or the
minimum number of data points for the interpolation step. This allows you to customize the
workflow for your own research. The workflow is designed to be generic,
so you can reuse it in different regions such as the Gulf of Finland or apply it
to analyze trends in other variables like temperature. Additionally, in the tools
section of Aqua Galaxy, you can search for Aqua Infra to access all the
developed OGCAPI processes used in the workflow.
Each process can be customized and used independently or integrated into new
workflows by adopting OGCAPI standards. These processes are
fully compatible with other initiatives such as the European digital twin of the
ocean. Let's conclude this training video by returning to the research story.
Based on the identified significant trends, the first research question addressed in this video has been
answered. Let's hear how Astra addresses the reviewed research question using the
results of the workflow. And I have to say that trend analysis confirmed the diverse intuition. Transparency is
decreasing and watercolor is changing in some of the regions in the Gulf of Riga.
But this is just the beginning. Our main research question is what environmental
processes are driving these changes in optical properties and how are they
connected to seasonal and land-based influences. So what began with a
divers's personal feeling has grown into a scientific investigation and we as a researchers
are excited to keep diving deeper. Astra and her research team will
continue this research by exploring the following questions. What explanatory components contribute
to the change in water optical properties? Are there any indications of
changes in riverine loads or concentrations of these components in rivers discharging into the Gulf of
Ria? Which activities and pressures such as land use or climate change are most
likely affecting the water's optical properties? And finally, which
socioeconomic drivers influence those activities? This video was created as
part of the Aqua Infra work package 6 led by the Bochum University of Applied
Sciences. On behalf of the Aqua Infra team, thank you for watching this training video. We appreciate your
interest in the Aqua Infra project and we hope it supports your research and encourages further exploration of Aqua
Infra tools and services. Together, let's make data driven research
fair and more impactful.